Guide to the Erwin Cotton Mills records, 1832-1976 and undated, bulk 1892-1967 RL.00366
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- William Allen Erwin series, 1871-1932; 5
  - Hunting, 1921-1930 and undated (Box 55)
  - Miscellaneous legal papers, 1927-1928 and undated (Box 55)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, undated (Box 55)
  - National Bank of Commerce, New York, 1928 (Box 55)
  - Photographs, approximately 1910s and 1932 (Box 55)
  - Property tax lists, 1894, 1927 (Box 55)
  - Protestant Episcopal Church, 1919-1928 and undated (Box 55)
  - Raleigh real estate, 1927-1928 (Box 55)
  - St. Mary's School, 1928 (Box 55)
  - St. Mary's School Building Committee, 1927-1928; 2 folders (Box 55)
  - St. Mary's School Building Committee, 1928 and undated (Box 56)
  - Salary; James B. Duke; Company financial statistics since 1892, 1910-1920; 2 folders (Box 56)
  - Sarah Erwin's National Cathedral School reports, 1915 (Box 56)
  - Southern Railway Pass with envelope cancelled on Train No. 16, 1899 (Box 56)
  - Stocks, Bonds, and Property of Mr. and Mrs. William A. Erwin and Mrs. Bessie S. Leak, 1920s (Box 56)
  - Tenant and other farm memoranda, 1916-1919 (Box 56)
  - Trial balances, 1927-1928 (Box 56)
  - Virginia Trust Company, 1923-1929 (Box 56)
  - Wachovia Bank and Trust Company, 1928 (Box 56)
- Pearl Cotton Mills series, 1892-1932; 6
  The Pearl Cotton Mills series consists of records from the 1890s until its absorption by Erwin Mills in 1932. The accounting records are represented through stock certificate books, ledgers, journals, trial balances, cash and bank account books, and inventories. The files are minimal but include the minutes and a variety of significant financial reports, statements, and other papers.
  - Appraisal, 1928 Sept. 28 (Box 56)
  - Appraisal, 1932 Feb. (Box 56)
  - Audit report, 1931 (Box 57)
  - Erwin Cotton Mills purchases and sales, 1927-1931 (Box 57)
  - Financial statements, 1909-1931 (Box 57)
  - Income tax returns, 1931-1932 (Box 57)
  - Inventories, 1931-1932 (Box 57)
  - Minutes of Directors and Stockholders, including charter and bylaws, 1892-1932 (Box 57)
  - N.C. Corporation Commission report, 1932 (Box 57)
  - Reports on estimated cost of repairs and replacements and on proposed labor complement and overhead, 1932 Feb. (Box 57)
  - Sale to Erwin Cotton Mills, 1932 (Box 57)
  - Secretary and Treasurer's reports, 1930-1931 (Box 57)
  - Statement of income and profit and loss, 1918-1928 (Box 57)
  - Stock certificate book, 1894-1928 (Volume 322)
  - Stock certificate book, 1928-1932 (Volume 323)
  - Ledger A, 1892-1899 (Volume 324)
  - Ledger B, 1900-1911 (Volume 325)
  - Ledger C, 1912-1923 (Volume 326)
  - Ledger D, 1924-1932 (Volume 327)
  - Journal B, 1907-1923 (Volume 328)
  - Journal C, 1923-1932 (Volume 329)
  - Trial balances, 1902-1916 (Volume 330)
  - Trial balances, 1917-1928 (Volume 331)
  - Trial balances, 1929-1932 (Volume 332)
  - Cash and bank account book, 1897-1899 (Volume 333)
  - Cash and bank account book, 1900-1904 (Volume 334)
  - Cash and bank account book, 1904-1910 (Volume 335)
  - Cash and bank account book, 1910-1916 (Volume 336)
  - Cash and bank account book, 1916-1920 (Volume 337)
  - Cash and bank account book, 1920-1923 (Volume 338)
  - Cash and bank account book, 1923-1927 (Volume 339)
  - Cash and bank account book, 1928-1932 (Volume 340)
  - Inventory book, 1906-1915 (Volume 341)
  - Inventory book, 1924-1930 (Volume 342)
  - Inventory book, 1931-1932 (Volume 343)
  - Inventory pricing calculations and related statistics, 1924-1932 (Volume 344)
- Cooleemee Cotton Mills series, 1899-1916; 7
  The Cooleemee Cotton Mills series contains primarily records from the late 1890s until its acquisition by Erwin Mills in 1906. Some material dates as late as 1916. The accounting volumes are ledgers, a journal, and cashbooks. There are minimal files but they include legal and financial papers as well as stock certificate books for the Cooleemee Water Power and Manufacturing Company.
  - Cooleemee Water Power and Manufacturing Company stock certificate book, 1899 (Box 58)
  - Denim styles, 1900 (Box 58)
  - Draper Company Account, 1904 (Box 58)
  - Goods manufactured, 1915 (Box 58)
  - Inventory book, 1907-1916 (Box 58)
  - Letterhead stationary, early 1900s (Box 58)
  - Lookout Shoals Property, Catawba River, 1900 (Box 58)
  - N.C. Corporation Commission report, 1902 (Box 58)
  - Property in Catawba, Iredell, and Alexander counties, and Farmers' crop liens with Virginia-Carolina Chemical Co., 1900-1907 (Box 58)
  - Stock certificate book, 1899-1903 (Box 58)
  - Survey of the South Yadkin River from Yadkin River to Cooleemee, including South River Mills, 1910-1911 (Box 58)
  - Current ledger, 1901-1906 (Volume 345)
  - Transfer Ledger No. 1, 1901-1905 (Volume 346)
  - Journal No. 1, 1901-1906 (Volume 347)
  - Cashbook No. 1, 1901-1903 (Volume 348)
  - Cashbook No. 2, 1904-1906 (Volume 349)
- Erwin Yarn Company series, 1919-1948; 8
  Records of the textile-selling agency at Philadelphia from its origin in the 1920s until its liquidation in the 1940s. Minutes, stockholder records, ledgers, journal, cashbook, and sales journal, and several files of legal and financial papers. Volumes arranged chronologically within types. Files arranged alphabetically.
  - Audit report, 1923 (Box 59)
  - Charter and dissolution papers, 1925-1947 (Box 59)
  - Federal tax records, 1925-1947; 2 folders (Box 59)
  - Gem Cotton Mills and Sevier Cotton Mills arbitration case, 1920 (Box 59)
  - Stockholder records, 1940-1947 (Box 59)
  - Minutes of stockholders and directors, 1925-1947 (Volume 350)
    Including certificate of incorporation and bylaws, 1925.
  - Stockholders ledger, 1925-1947 (Volume 351)
  - Stock certificate book, 1925-1940 (Volume 352)
  - Ledger, 1925-1947 (Volume 353)
  - Private ledger, 1919-1947 (Volume 354)
    Employee payroll and sales records
  - Journal, 1942-1947 (Volume 355)
  - Cashbook, 1944-1948 (Volume 356)
  - Sales journal, 1944-1947 (Volume 357)
- J. N. Ledford Company series, 1901-1963; 9
  The J. N. Ledford Company series contains records of this department store in Cooleemee, N.C., from its origin in 1901 until the 1960s. William Allen Erwin was an original stockholder, and by 1919 Erwin Mills was the majority stockholder. Files include minutes, stockholder records, and scattered legal and financial papers and volumes. Some workers at Cooleemee Mills are identifiable through the Accounts Receivable.
  - Information folder, undated (Box 59)
  - Minutes of stockholders and directors, 1901-1938 (Box 59)
    Including certificate of incorporation and bylaws, 1901.
  - Minutes of stockholders and directors, 1938-1946 (Box 60)
  - Minutes of stockholders and directors, 1946-1955 (Box 60)
  - Minutes of stockholders and directors, 1955-1963 (Box 60)
    Including certificate of incorporation, 1901; bylaws, 1955-1958; correspondence, 1955-1956.
  - Stock certificate book, 1902-1954 (Box 61)
  - Audit reports, 1941-1952, 1954-1961 (Box 61)
  - Ledger, 1958-1963 (Box 61)
  - Journal, 1958-1963 (Box 61)
  - Financial statements and other papers, 1938-1953; 3 folders (Box 62)
  - Accounts receivable, 1938 (Box 62)
  - Assignments and transfers of accounts payable, 1938; 4 folders (Box 62)
  - Correspondence, 1918, 1956-1958 (Box 62)